Guide to the Citizens for New Columbia collection, 1982-1994 MS2383
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Citizens for New Columbia collection
1993-1994
1930, 1982 - 1994
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
demczuk, Bernard
Citizens for New Columbia
MS2383
2.5 Linear Feet 3 document boxes, 1 flat box
Citizens for New Columbia was a statehood advocacy group active in the early 1990s that actively supported statehood for D.C. The group was a pro-statehood grass-roots group working to promote citizen participation using civil disobedience and congressional lobbying in advance of the initial House vote. Prominent members of the group included former mayors of Washington D.C. Sharon Pratt and Walter Washington, Congresswoman Eleanor Holmes Norton, Senator Jesse L. Jackson, and Senator Florence Pendleton. This collection contains planning documents, fliers, posters, buttons, memorabilia, cartoons, editorials, correspondence, editorials, and handwritten materials for the Citizens for New Columbia, an organization that worked towards D.C. Statehood. The records date from 1982-1994, but most of the records date from 1993-1994.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
Organized into 3 series: Organizations, direct action, proposed legal measures, Promotional materials, event planning, publicity, and Governance.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred by Division of External Relations, 2018 December 04 (2018.049)
Historical note
Citizens for New Columbia was a statehood advocacy group active in the early 1990s that actively supported statehood for D.C. The group was a pro-statehood grass-roots group working to promote citizen participation using civil disobedience and congressional lobbying in advance of the initial House vote.
Prominent members of the group included former mayors of Washington D.C. Sharon Pratt and Walter Washington, Congresswoman Eleanor Holmes Norton, Senator Jesse L. Jackson, and Senator Florence Pendleton.
Community engagement was a core part of their strategy. They encouraged community members to contribute as volunteers and donors and tied the issue of self-determination to other social issues D.C. residents were facing. They hosted walks for independence, organized summits and award ceremonies, circulated newsletters, and corresponded with other grassroots groups to strategize. Their belief in self-determination, full citizenship, and congressional representation
Scope and Contents
This collection contains promotional fliers, mock-ups of fliers, planning documents, organizing materials (chant sheets, notes about legal/media strategies, demonstration handbook) political cartoons, news releases, correspondence, drafts of editorials, magazines, buttons, branded plastic bags, policy documentation, and reports related to the working of the organization Citizens for New Columbia as they worked to promote D.C. Statehood. The records date from 1982-1994, but most of the records date from 1993-1994.
Statehood (American politics) -- Washington (D.C.); Washington (D.C.) Politics and government; Political activists; demczuk, Bernard
- Organizations, direct action, proposed legal measures, 1982-1994; Series 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains correspondence between the Citizens of New Columbia and other organizations, fundraising materials, letters of support or opposition to establishing statehood, and other materials related to organizing and direct action. They primarily range from 1993-1994, but some records date from 1982.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Canvas, 1993-1993; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence [1 of 2], 1993-1993; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence [2 of 2], 1993-1993; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Direct action [1 of 2], 1992-1993; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    One document in this folder may have a missing page
  - Direct action [2 of 2], 1993-1993; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Endorsements--statehood, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Fundraising committee agendas, 1993-1993; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - HR51 bill + amendments, 1993-1993; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Legal, 1993-1993; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Legal and governmental documents, 1991-1994; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Proposed legal measures, 1982-1987; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Memos, 1993-1993; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Opposition, 1993-1993; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Support and opposition, 1991-1993; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Resolutions -- statehood, 1991-1991; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - [Jim] Sasser, 1993-1993; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Sign-in sheets, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - U.E. (New Haven), 1989-1990; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - UFCW Local 400, 1990-1990; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - UPIU L-14: Jay, me., 1990-1990; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - UPIU local 654, 1990-1990; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Promotional materials, event planning, publicity, 1930, 1993-1994; 1993-1994; Series 2
  This series contains materials that were distributed to members of the organization and the general public to promote events and inform readers about statehood and self-determination. Some of these materials are oversized.
  - Articles, 1992-1993; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - CNC memorabilia and promotional materials, 1993-1994; Series 2 (Box 4, Flat box 4)
    This box contains oversized materials that were intended to promote the Citizens of New Columbia. Materials include folders with the CNC logo, markups of stickers, buttons, plastic bags, proclamations, resolutions, awards, and the Citizens of New Columbia newspaper.
  - December 1 awards, 1993-1993; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Editorial, 1993-1993; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Flag, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Media/News Releases, 1993-1993; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - News Conference, 1993-1993; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - NO!, 1993-1993; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - National Outreach -- Statehood, 1993-1993; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - NYTimes, 1992-1992; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Pictures, 1993-1993; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Printing, 1993-1993; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Poetry/Pictures, [undated]; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Promotional Materials [1 of 3], 1993-1994; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Promotional Materials [2 of 3], 1993-1994; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Promotional Materials [3 of 3], 1993-1994; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Publications [1 of 2], 1993-1993; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Publications [2 of 2], 1993-1994; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Story of Flag -- Star 51, [undated]; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Summit Follow-Up, 1993-1993; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Summit planning, 1993-1993; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Statehood transition, 1989-1994; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Symbols, 1930-1993; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Governance, 1991-1994; Series 3
  This series contains documents related to planning, the structure of the organization, correspondence between members, and financial documents. These materials were distributed to members of the organization.
  - Agendas [1 of 2], 1993-1994; Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Agendas [2 of 2], 1993-1994; Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Agendas - gen. mtgs., 1993-1993; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence between members, 1991-1993; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Inter-organizational materials [1 of 2], 1993-1994; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Inter-organizational materials [2 of 2], 1993-1994; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - LCCR - statehood, 1993-1993; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Meeting notes [1 of 2], 1993-1994; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Meeting notes [2 of 2], 1993-1994; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Organizational structure, [undated]; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - POA [Plan of Action] clean, 1993-1993; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Statehood Education Foundation forms, 1993-1993; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 10)